<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<link rev="made" href="mailto:esr@snark.thyrsus.com" />
<link rel="stylesheet" href="/~esr/sitestyle.css" type="text/css" />
<meta name="description" content="" />
<meta name="keywords" content="" />
<meta name="MSSmartTagsPreventParsing" content="TRUE" />
<title>The Luxury of Ignorance: An Open-Source Horror Story</title>
</head>
<body>

<div id="Header">
<table width="100%" cellpadding="0" summary="Canned page header">
<tr>
<td>The Luxury of Ignorance: An Open-Source Horror Story</td>
<td align="right">
<script language="JavaScript" src="/~esr/datestamp.js" type='text/javascript'></script>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div>

<div id="Menu">
	<hr/>
	<a href="/~esr" title="My home page">Home Page</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/whatsnew.html" title="What's new on this site">What's New</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/sitemap.html" title="Map of the site">Site Map</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/software.html" title="Software I maintain">Software</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/projects.html" title="My projects">Projects</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/faqs/" title="My FAQ documents">HOWTOs</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/writings/" title="Essays and ruminations">Essays</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/personal.html" title="Portrait of the author">Personal</a><br />
	<a href="http://www.ibiblio.org/esrblog/">Weblog</a><br/>	
	<a href="/~esr/netfreedom/">Freedom!</a><br />
	<a href="/~esr/guns/">Firearms!</a><br />
	<hr/>
</div>

<div id="Content">

<div class='notebox'>A translation to <a href='http://www.kubieziel.de/computer/cups-horror.html'>German</a> is available.</div>

<p>I've just gone through the experience of trying to configure CUPS,
the Common Unix Printing System.  It has proved a textbook lesson in
why nontechnical people run screaming from Unix.  This is all the more
frustrating because the developers of CUPS have obviously tried hard
to produce an accessible system &mdash; but the best intentions and
effort have led to a system which despite its superficial
pseudo-friendliness is so undiscoverable that it might as well have
been written in ancient Sanskrit.</p>

<p>GUI tools and voluminous manuals are not enough.  You have to think
about what the actual user experiences when he or she sits down to do
actual stuff, and you have to think about it <em>from the user's point
of view</em>.  The CUPS people, despite good intentions, have utterly
failed at this.  I'm going to anatomize this failure in detail,
because there are lessons here that other open-source projects would
do well to heed.  The point of this essay is not, therefore, just to 
beat up on the CUPS people &mdash; it's also to beat up on every other
open-source designer who does equally thoughtless things under the
fond delusion that a slick-looking UI is a well-designed UI.  Watch 
and learn...</p>

<p>The configuration problem is simple.  I have a desktop machine
named 'snark'.  It is connected, via the house Ethernet, to my wife
Cathy's machine, which is named 'minx'.  Minx has a LaserJet 6MP
attached to it via parallel port.  Both machines are running Fedora
Core 1, and Cathy can print locally from minx.  I can ssh minx from
snark, so the network is known good.</p>

<br/>
<p>This should be easy, right?  *hollow laughter*  Famous last words...</p>
<br/>

<p>First, I do what any nontechnical user would do.  I go to my desktop menu 
and click System Settings->Printing, then give the root password to the
following popup.  Up comes a "Printer configuration" popup.  I click
"New".  Up pops a wizard that says, in big friendly letters, "Add a new
print queue".  So far, so good.  I click "Forward".</p>

<p>Now, those of you who are intimate with CUPS know I have already
made a basic error.  I shouldn't be trying to create a new print queue
on snark and then glue it to the server on minx, at all.  Instead, if
I want to pass print jobs to minx, I should look at the configuration
wizard, see minx's print queue already announced there, and make it
snark's default.  <em>But nothing in the configuration wizard's
interface even hints at that!</em>  And minx's print queue does not show,
for a reason we'll discover later in this sorry saga.</p>

<p>New form in the window, saying "Queue name" in equally big friendly letters.
It offers a default of "printer".  I change it to "laserjet" because I might
at some point want to hook up the ancient dot-matrix thingy I still have.
I enter the optional short description: "the laser printer".  So far this
is all good.  Aunt Tillie could handle this just fine.  Forward...</p>

<p>New form.  "Queue type", it says.  There's a drop-down menu.  The default 
is "Locally connected", which is reasonable.  Clicking on the menu, I am
presented with the following alternatives:</p>

<pre>
	Networked CUPS (IPP)
	Networked Unix (LPD)
	Networked Windows (SMB)
	Networked Novell (NCP)
	Networked JetDirect
</pre>

<p>Here is our first intimation of trouble.  If I were Aunt Tillie the
archetypal nontechnical user, I am at this point thinking "What in the
holy fleeping frack does that mean?  And just as importantly, <em>why
do I have to answer this question?</em>" I do not, after all, have any
Windows machines on my network.  Nor any Netware boxes.  And I
certainly don't have a "Networked JetDirect", whatever <em>that</em>
might be.</p>

<p>If the designers were half-smart about UI issues (like, say, Windows
programmers) they'd probe the local network neighborhood and omit the
impossible entries.  If they were really smart (like, say, Mac
programmers) they'd leave the impossible choices in but gray them out,
signifying that if your system were configured a bit differently you
really could print on a Windows machine, assuming you were unfortunate
enough to own one.</p>

<p>But no.  Instead, Aunt Tillie is already getting the idea that this 
software was written by geeks without clue.</p>

<p>But wait!  Wait!  Hallelujah!  There's a help button!  I click it.
Up comes a nice glossy page of on-line documentation.  But instead of
answering the question in my mind, which is "How do I choose the right
queue type", it is a page on adding a locally connected printer.  That
is, it's associated with the currently selected-by-default queue type,
not the operation of choosing a queue.  The help is...unhelpful.</p>

<p>Aunt Tillie, at this point, is either resigning herself to another
session of being tortured by the poor UI choices of well-meaning idiots
or deciding to chuck this whole Linux thing and go back to the old
Windows box.  It blue-screened a lot, but at least it allowed her the
luxury of ignorance &mdash; she didn't have to know, or care, about
what a JetDirect or a CUPS might be.</p>

<p>I am not ignorant, but I have my own equivalent of Aunt Tillie's
problem.  I know I want one of the top two methods, but I don't know
which one.  And <em>I</em> don't want to know or care about the
difference either; I have better things to do with my brain than
clutter it with sysadminning details.  If the tool can detect that
both methods are available on the local net (and that shouldn't be
hard, they're both well-known ports) it should put "(recommended)"
next to one so I can click and keep going.</p>

<p>But nooooo.  Instead I have to stare at the help screen and think
"Where might I find some guidance on this, and why is this already taking
too freaking long?"  Applying my fearsome hacker-jutsu, I try clicking
"Prev".  I get a page about the printer configuration which describes
the queue types, but still no guidance on how to choose between CUPS
and LPD.</p>

<p>Obviously it never occurred to the designers of the CUPS that this
could be an issue, either for Aunt Tillie or for the more technically
ept.  There is no large friendly button next to the "Select a queue
type" that says "How to select a queue type".  This lack is a grave
flaw in the UI design that turns the superficial spiffiness of the
configuration wizard into a tease, a mockery.</p>

<p>Applying my fearsome hacker-jutsu once again, I guess, and select
"CUPS (IPP)".  Comes now the form that turns the UI from a mockery to
something worse. It presents two text fields. One is labeled "Server"
and is blank.  The other is labeled "Path:" and contains the string
"/printers/queue1".</p>

<p>If Aunt Tillie were still along for the ride, she would be using
some unladylike language right about now.  And with good reason,
because this is a crash landing, an unmitigated disaster.  To
understand why, you have to stop thinking like a hacker for a few
moments.  Cram your mind, if you can, back into the mindset of a
clueless user.  Somebody who not only doesn't know what a string like
"/printers/queue1" might mean, but doesn't want to know, and doesn't
think he or she ought to have to learn.</p>

<p>From Aunt Tillie's point of view, it's reasonable that the host
field is empty; she hasn't selected one, after all.  But the fact that
the Path field is filled in is worse than useless, it's actually
harmful &mdash; because she doesn't know what it means, and doesn't
know how to tell whether or not that default would be valid if she
<em>did</em> fill in a server name.  She is stopped dead.</p>

<p> What she ought at this point to be seeing is one of two things:
either a list of CUPS print queues available on the local network,
or a big bold message that says "I don't see any queues available
locally; you may need to go set up a print server."  The prompt
for server/path, presented here, is a stone wall; not only 
does it leaves Aunt Tillie with no idea how to proceed, it is
just as opaque to an experienced hacker like me.</p>

<p>The meta-problem here is that the configuration wizard does all the
approved rituals (GUI with standardized clicky buttons, help popping
up in a browser, etc. etc.) but doesn't have the central attribute
these are supposed to achieve: <em>discoverability</em>. That is, the
quality that every point in the interface has prompts and actions
attached to it from which you can <em>learn what to do next</em>. 
Does <em>your</em> project have this quality?</p>

<p>In fact, the "Queue type" form is an anti-discoverable interface
&mdash; it leads you right down a blind alley of trying to set up a
local queue pointing to a remote server that you <em>know</em> can
print &mdash; like my wife Cathy's machine &mdash; and then cursing
because your test print attempts fail.  This is, in fact, exactly what
happened to me next.</p>

<p>I typed "minx.thyrsus.com" into the server field, on the assumption
that "/printers/queue1" might be a safe default that other CUPS
instances would honor.  I went through the manufacturer and model
screens and confirmed the queue creation. The wizard popped up a
window offering to print a test page; I told it yes...and nothing
happened. Actually, it was worse than nothing; the configurator window
displayed a message that said `Network host "minx.thyrsus.com" is
busy, will retry in 30 seconds', and then (to all appearances)
hung.</p>

<p>We are now deep in the trackless swamps created by thoughtless,
feckless UI design &mdash; full of glitz and GUI, signifying nothing.
This is the precise point at which I decided I was going to write a rant
and started taking notes.</p>

<p>The "Queue type" screen gave me no clue about the existence,
nonexistence, or sharable status of any print queues on my network.  I
have two other machines in the house, both running full Fedora Core
and plugged into Ethernet; the <em>really</em> right thing would have
been a message that said "I see CUPS demons are running on minx, golux,
and grelber, but no queues are accessible." with a pointer
into the CUPS documentation.</p>

<p>Again, the help I did get wasn't helpful.  The page associated with
"Networked CUPS (IPP) Printer" says "Any networked IPP printer found
via CUPS browsing appears in the main window under the <b>Browsed
queues</b> category."  Oh, really?  What "main window" would that be
in? And it doesn't give me a clue what to do if I don't see any
<b>Browsed queues</b> category, which is particularly wack since that
is the normal, default situation for a new installation!</p>

<p>None of this is rocket science.  The problem isn't that the right
things are technically difficult to do; CUPS is already supposed to
have discovery of active shareable queues as a feature.  The problem
is that the CUPS designers' <em>attitude</em> was wrong.  They never
stepped outside their assumptions.  They never exerted the mental
effort to forget what they know and sit down at the system like a dumb
user who's never seen it before &mdash; and they never watched a dumb
user in action!</p>

<p>CUPS is not alone.  This kind of fecklessness is endemic in
open-source land.  And it's what's keeping Microsoft in business
&mdash; because by Goddess, they may write crappy insecure overpriced
shoddy software, but on this <em>one issue</em> their half-assed 
semi-competent best is an order of magnitude better than we usually
manage.</p>

<p>But enough prescriptive ranting for the moment.  I'm going to
tell you about my efforts to research my way out of this hole, 
because there are some lessons there as well.  First, I went looking
for documentation.  I did this in a Unix-hackerish way, by eyeballing
the output of `locate printers` for anything in /usr/share/doc related to
CUPS.  I found /usr/share/doc/cups-1.1.19/printers/index.html and
fired up a browser on it.  It redirected me to http://localhost:631/
which was OK, though the redirect went by too fast.</p>

<p>And I found myself looking at a web page that was not obviously
useful for troubleshooting my problem.  I tried clicking on the button
marked "Administration" in hopes the tool behind it would be a bit
more discoverable than the configuration.  I got a password
prompt.</p>

<p>Hello?  How am I supposed to know what to do with <em>this</em>
thing? All it tells me is that it wants a "CUPS login".  Is this the
same as a system root login, or is there some special funky CUPS
identity I'm supposed to telepathically know about?  The prompt on
these password popups is configurable; it could have offered me a clue
and a pointer into the documentation.  It didn't.</p>

<p>Once again, the theme is the absence of discoverability.  That
password prompt, rather than being a signpost leading further into
an understanding of the system, was another stone wall.</p>

<p>When all else fails, there's always Google.  I searched on "CUPS
printing HOWTO" and found a link to "The Linux Printing HOWTO" &mdash;
which when I chased it, turned out to be a 404.  Now that bit is
probably not the CUPS designers' fault; I'm throwing it in just to
establish that, at that point, I was feeling screwed, blued, and
tatooed.  The shiny-surfaced opacity of CUPS had, it seemed,
defeated me in what should have been a trivial 30-second task.</p>

<p>I persevered, however.  My next step was to ssh into minx and see
if I could discover the name of the active CUPS queue.  Maybe, I
thought, if I found that out I could plug that queue name into the
configuration wizard on snark and it would all work.  Alas, it was not
to be.  The two commands that seemed possibly relevant were lpinfo(8) 
and lpadmin, and you can't get a list of queue names from either of
them.  The output of "lpinfo -v" looked like it ought to be useful,
but I had no idea how to map these device URLs onto queue names.</p>

<p>We are now in real time.  I am writing this rant as I am trying to
figure out the path out of this maze. I am reading the CUPS System
Administrator's Manual and it claims : "CUPS supports automatic client
configuration of printers on the same subnet. To configure printers on
the same subnet, do nothing. Each client should see the available
printers within 30 seconds automatically. The printer and class lists
are updated automatically as printers and servers are added or
removed."  Well, that's very nice, but the breezy confidence of their
exposition leaves me with no clue about what to do when the
autoconfiguration isn't working!</p>

<p>I'm reading the manual, and I find a reference to "BrowseAddress"
and /etc/cups/cupsd.conf which begins to unfold for me the mystery of
how the autoconfiguration is supposed to work.  It seems that CUPS
instances periodically send broadcast packets advertising their status
and available printers to a broadcast address to be picked up by other
CUPS instances.  Smart design!  But...bugger me with a chainsaw, the
broadcast facility is turned off by default <em>and the documentation
doesn't tell you that!</em></p>

<p>So, let's review.  In order for the nice, user-friendly
autoconfiguration stuff to work, you have to first edit an /etc file.
On a different machine than the one you're trying to set up.  You
have to read the comments in configuration file to know that you need
to do this in the first place.</p>

<p>What a truly lovely, classic blunder this is.  That they turned off
the autoconfiguration support is understandable from a
security-engineering point of view.  But failing to mention this in
the Administrator's Guide, and failing to warn the user during the
configuration-wizard dialogue that operating printers may not be
visible unless your site admin has performed the appropriate ritual on
the printers' host machines...that is moronically thoughtless.</p>

<p>This kind of crap is exactly why Linux has had such trouble gaining
traction among nontechnical users &mdash; and it becomes less
forgivable, not more, when it's surrounded by a boatload of GUI 
cotton candy that adds complexity without actually delivering
friendliness to the user.</p>

<p>I edit a correct broadcast address for my network into
/etc/cups/cupsd.conf on minx.  I am unsurprised to learn that the
cupsd(8) man page doesn't tell me whether the standard <code>kill
-HUP</code> will force cupsd to reread that file, because at this
point I am expecting the documentation to be unhelpful. I do
<code>/etc/init.d/cups restart</code> instead.</p>

<p>I write the last paragraph, then go back to the configuration
wizard.  A little poking at it discloses an Action->Sharing item.  
When I click the OK button, "Browsed queues" appears in the wizard
window.  Excelsior!  It appears that snark is now receiving broadcast
configuration info from minx.  And sure enough, when I click "Browse
queues" a LaserJet 6 shows up as a device.  Curiously, however, it is
labeled "lp0" without any indication that it's not on the local
machine.</p>

<p>I fire up the Web interface.  Sure enough, it finds the LaserJet 6 
on minx.  But not all is goodness.  When I try to print a test page,
a popup tells me "The connection was refused when attempting to contact
minx.thyrsus.com:631".</p>

<p>I am again unsurprised to learn that neither the user's nor the
Administrator's Guide has anything to say about troubleshooting CUPS
problems.  The lpr(1) interface is massively unhelpful; 
when I submit jobs from snark, they appear to vanish into a black
hole.</p>

<p>Eventually I notice the Listen directive in the
/etc/cups/cupsd.conf file.  "Aha!" says I to myself, "Maybe this is
like sendmail, where you have to tell it explicitly to listen on the
server's IP address." I add "Listen 192.168.1.21", the latter being
minx's IP address, restarts cupsd...and lo and behold my test job
comes tumbling out of the printer.</p>

<p>The thing to notice here is how far behind we have left Aunt
Tillie.  Rule 1 of writing software for nontechnical users is this: if
they have to read documentation to use it <em>you designed it
wrong</em>.  The interface of the software should be all the
documentation the user needs.  You'd have lost the non-techie before
the point in this troubleshooting sequence where a hacker like me even
got fully engaged.</p>

<p>But in this case, the documentation was passively but severely
misleading in one area, and harmfully silent in others.  I eventually
had to apply m4d skillz gained from wrestling with sendmail to solve a
problem the CUPS documentation never even hinted about.</p>

<p>As I said before, the point of this essay is not especially to bash
on the CUPS guys.  They're no worse than thousands of projects out
there, and that <em>is</em> the point.  We talk about world
domination, but we'll neither have it nor deserve it until we learn to
do better than this.  A <em>lot</em> better.</p>

<p>It's not like doing better would be difficult, either.  None of the
changes in CUPS behavior or documentation I've described would be
technical challenges; the problem is that these simple things never
occurred to developers who bring huge amounts of already-acquired
knowledge to bear every time they look at their user interfaces.</p>

<p>So, if you are out there writing GUI apps for Linux or BSD or
whatever, here are some questions you need to be asking yourself:</p>

<ol>
<li>What does my software look like to a non-technical user who has
    never seen it before?</li>

<li>Is there any screen in my GUI that is a dead end, without giving
guidance further into the system?</li>

<li>The requirement that end-users read documentation is a sign of UI
    design failure.  Is my UI design a failure?</li>

<li>For technical tasks that do require documentation, do they 
fail to mention critical defaults?</li>

<li>Does my project welcome and respond to usability feedback from
non-expert users?</li>
 
<li>And, most importantly of all...do I allow my users the precious
    luxury of ignorance?</li>
</ol>

<hr/>
<p>Postscript, 26 Feb 2004: I added the new fifth question based on an
excellent suggestion in LWN's comments on the story.</p>

<p>And here are some more design rules, from Nico Kadel-Garcia:</p>

<ul>
<li>Can you gracefully and easily duplicate your tools and configuration for
a similar installation? Is it documented?  (RedHat and CUPS is no help with
this, either, most of the print-drivers wend their way from the foomatic and
other tools into the CUPS setups without a lot of hint of how it works.)
[For cups, the answer is "you can duplicate it easily, but it's a *secret*"!
Every configuration should be built and recompiled from the source tarball!
What are you, a n00b?]</li>

<li>Is installing this toolset likely to replace or break something already
in place (such as LPD based printing packages)? If so, explain how to
gracefully do the transition.</li>

<li>Are there settings you can do from the command line or hand-editing
config files that <em>cannot</em> be done from the GUI? Are they documented
anywhere? Does using the GUI erase these settings? (The answer for CUPS is
"Yes, you can flush all sorts of hand-edited things this way!". This was an
incredible problem for NeXT stations and remains a big freeware GUI problem,
although most try harder to address this. Webmin is an excellent example of
how to do it right in most cases!)</li>

<li>Are all your important features mentioned? The automatic flat
text->Postscript conversion is one such feature, and despite its presence in
the tarball tools and default use the CUPS claim it's not theirs and not
their problem.</li>
</ul>

<p>PPS, 27 Feb: Got a very positive response from the CUPS folks.  At
least some of these things will be fixed.</p>

<p>PPPS, 29 Feb: I have written a followup on 
<a href='luxury-part-deux.html'>the luxury of ignorance</a>.</p>

<p>There is now a site for projects looking for usability advice and 
interaction designers who want to help.  It is 
<a href="http://openusability.org">openusability.org</a>.</p>

</div>
<hr />
</body>
</html>

<!--
Local Variables:
compile-command: "(cd ~/WWW; upload writings/cups-horror.html)"
End:
-->










#####EOF#####


<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<title>Eric S. Raymond's Home Page</title>
<link rev="made" href="mailto:esr@snark.thyrsus.com" />
<link rel="stylesheet" href="sitestyle.css" type="text/css"  />
<meta name="description" content="Everything about my Internet projects." />
</head>
<body>

<div id="Header">
<table width="100%" cellpadding="0" summary="Canned page header">
<tr>
<td width="80%">
Eric S. Raymond's Home Page
</td>
<td width="20%" align="right">
<script language="JavaScript" src="/~esr/datestamp.js" type='text/javascript'></script>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div>

<div id="Menu">
	<hr/>
	Home page<br />
	<a href="sitemap.html" title="Map of the site">Site Map</a><br />
	<a href="whatsnew.html" title="What's new on this site">What's New</a><br />
	<a href="software.html" title="Software I maintain">Software</a><br />
	<a href="projects.html" title="My projects">Projects</a><br />
	<a href="faqs/" title="My FAQ documents">HOWTOs</a><br />
	<a href="writings/" title="Essays and ruminations">Essays</a><br />
	<a href="personal.html" title="Portrait of the author">Personal</a><br />
	<a href="http://esr.ibiblio.org/">Weblog</a><br/>
	<a href="press.html" title="Tips for reporters">For Journalists</a><br />
	<a href="netfreedom/">Freedom!</a><br />
	<a href="guns/">Firearms!</a><br />
	<a href="who-is-ESR.html">Who Is ESR?</a><br />
	<hr/>
	<a href='jargon/' title="The Jargon File, aka The New Hacker's Dictionary">
		<img src='/~esr/graphics/nhd3-small.jpg' alt=""/></a>
	<br clear='left' />
	<a href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/cathbazpaper/"
		title="The Cathedral and the Bazaar">
		<img src="/~esr/graphics/cb.s.png" alt="" /></a>
	<br clear='left' />
	<a href="writings/taoup/" title="The Art of Unix Programming">
		<img src="/~esr/graphics/taoup.s.png" alt="" /></a>
	<hr/>
	<a href="mailto:esr@thyrsus.com" title='esr@thyrsus.com'>Email me</a>
	<hr/>

    <p>
      <a href="http://validator.w3.org/check/referer"><img
          src="http://www.w3.org/Icons/valid-xhtml10"
          alt="Valid XHTML 1.0!" height="31" width="88" /></a>
    </p>
    </div>

<div id="Content">

<p>Welcome to my piece of the Web. I maintain quite a lot of <a
href="http://www.opensource.org">open-source</a> software, FAQs,
and HTML documents, so this site is rather complex. It's mostly
validated HTML and light on the graphics, though. You won't have to
wait an eon for any of the pages to load.</p>

<p>If the software and FAQs I maintain are valuable to you (and especially
if my software makes you money) please <a
href="https://www.patreon.com/esr">leave me a tip.</a></p>

<h1>Using this site</h1>

<p>If you want to link to, copy, mirror, or translate portions of this
site, please read my <a href="copying.html">copying policy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.anybrowser.org/campaign/"> <img
src="graphics/w3c_ab.png" align="right" alt="viewable with any
browser" border="0"/></a>If the HTML or images on this site seem
to be confusing your browser, see the <a href='site-design.html'>site
design notes</a>.</p>

<h1>Frequently-Asked Questions</h1>

<p>If you're with the press, or want me to give a talk, here are
answers to the <a href="press.html">usual questions</a>. You can see a
list of my upcoming <a href="speaking.html">speaking
engagements</a>.</p>

<p>If you're looking for the Halloween Documents, they're <a
href="halloween/">here</a>.  Having studied the history of other
advocacy organizations, I specifically designed OSI not to be a
founder-centered cult of personality; I think OSI's decision to move
them off the OSI website was a mistake, but our community is healthier
because they had the power to make that mistake.</p>

<h1>It's all about freedom...</h1>

<p><img src="graphics/pgp-now.png" align="right" width="88"
height="31" alt="PGP NOW! image" /> You can fetch my <a
href="gpg-public-key.asc">GPG public key</a> here. I support
widespread use of strong cryptography for privacy, and encourage
you to use GPG encryption with this key when sending me messages.
If your mailer makes this difficult, consider switching to <a
href="http://www.mutt.org">Mutt</a>.</p>

<p>As a public service and act of civil disobedience, we are proud
to offer the <a href="css-auth.tar.gz">DeCSS</a> code that will
allow you to circumvent the encryption on the DVDs you own. Your
DVD, your hardware, your choice! (Please do not ask me technical
questions about this code; I have never used it.)</p>

<p>Also, here is the decryption key used for most HD-DVD movies:</p>

<p>09 F9 11 02 9D 74 E3 5B D8 41 56 C5 63 56 88 C0</p>

<p>I have never used this, either, I'm publishing it here because the
MPAA is attempting to suppress public knowledge of it.</p>

<p>Finally, <a href="hdcp-master.txt">the HDCP master key</a>.  These
magic bits defeat the HDCP scrambling that attempt to prevent you from 
viewing high-definition video on the hardware of your choice.  (No,
I've never used this either.)</p>

<p> I will not tolerate having general-purpose computing hardware,
which should be an instrument of liberation and creativity, reduced to
a locked-down delivery pipe for "content". By trying to cripple my
tools, the big-media machine has made me its enemy. DRM delenda est!</p>

<h1>...and it's all about me.</h1>

<p>You can read all about my <a href="projects.html">projects</a>,
past present and future, including the software and FAQs and Web
resources I maintain.</p>

<p>I do consulting under the <strong>Thyrsus Enterprises</strong>
service mark. You can surf to my <a href="resume.html">resume</a>
from here, if you're interested in my career or qualifications. I'm
not in the market for a job just now, though, unless you can offer
a project that really fascinates me.</p>

<p>You can read <a href="personal.html">personal stuff</a> about my
life and politics and hobbies and friends. You may also find my <a
href="writings/">writings</a> of interest.</p>

</div>

<!--
Local Variables:
compile-command: "(cd ~/WWW; upload index.html)"
End:
-->
</body>
</html>




#####EOF#####


